かああ くうう
かああ くううう
かか
くう くう
かあ うう うう
I can't even fly where I please now.
わしは今は空を飛ぶこともできんがな
But this, too, shall pass.
しかしこんなのは一時のことだ
One day, when my back stops hurting
.and I get back in shape,
いずれ腰も治って調子が戻ったら
I'll teach you all kinds of things.
また色々なことを教えてやろう
If I put my mind to it,
I can move the very mountains
わしだってその気になれば
山を動かすこともできるのだし
and topple buildings with naught
.but the power of the wind.
辻風でビルをなぎ倒すことだってできるんだ
Yeah. I know you can.
はい きっとそうでしょうとも
うう
What a pitiful state to be in.
このままではあんまり情けない
But one day, everything under the heavens
.will once again be within my reach.
必ずまた天が下に大いに悪戯をしてやろう
Master, you should
.really get some sleep.
先生
どうかお休みくださいな
うう 眠るさ 眠る
I know, I know.
You should stay the night
.every now and then.
お前もたまにはここで寝ておゆき
かああ く
んん
か かあ
かあ
はあ 嘆かわしい
This is so sad.
It's been 1,200 years since Emperor Kammu
.settled on a location for his palace.
桓武天皇が往生の地を定めてより
千二百年
Humans live in the city,
tanuki crawl the earth,
人間は街に暮らし 狸は地を這い
and tengu fly the skies.
天狗は天空を飛行する
Since Kyoto's establishment,
平安遷都この方続く 人間と狸と天狗の三つ巴
humans, tanuki, and tengu
.have maintained a delicate balance.
That's what keeps the great wheel of this city
.turning round and round.
それがこの街の大きな車輪をぐるぐる回している
And watching that wheel spin
.is more fun than anything else.
回る車輪を眺めているのが
どんなことより面白い
I'm what you'd call a tanuki
私はいわゆる狸であるが
but too proud to be a mere tanuki.
ただ一介の狸であることを潔しとせず
I admire tengu from afar,
and I love imitating humans.
天狗に遠く憧れて 人間を真似るのも大好きだ
That's why my daily life is busy enough
.to make your head spin.
従って我が日常は目まぐるしく
In fact, there's no time
.to be bored at all.
退屈している暇が無い
omoshiroku nai yo no naka
You just have to make
面白くない世の中
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
omoshiroku sureba ii sa
this dull world more interesting
面白くすればいいさ
omoshiroku sureba ii sa
this dull world more interesting
tsumaranee no ga kuchiguse nano wa
Some people love to claim that something is boring
“つまらねえ”のが口癖なのは
tsumaranee no ga kuchiguse nano wa
Some people love to claim that something is boring
sore koso honto ni tsumaranai
That habit is the most boring thing of all
それこそホントにつまらない
sore koso honto ni tsumaranai
That habit is the most boring thing of all
monku wo iu no wa kantan dakedo
It's easy to complain about stuff
文句を言うのは簡単だけど
monku wo iu no wa kantan dakedo
It's easy to complain about stuff
dareka wa nannmo kurenai
but it doesn't do any good at all
誰かは何もくれない
dareka wa nannmo kurenai
but it doesn't do any good at all
hashiranai kedo tomari wa shinai
That sort of useless waste of time
走らないけど止まりはしない
dare ni mo nagareru ahou no chi
runs in our idiot blood
誰にも流れる阿呆の血
sawageba sawagu hodo kakitateru
Just party on and on, and the more you do
騒げば騒ぐ程かき立てる
nanto subarashiki hibi
the more awesome will be your days
なんと素晴らしき日々
omoshiroku nai yo no naka
You just have to make
面白くない世の中
omoshiroku sureba ii no sa
this dull world more interesting
面白くすればいいのさ
jibun de mitsukerya
The things you find for yourself in this world
自分で見つけりゃ
hodohodo ni paradaisu da
quickly turn it into a little paradise
ほどほどにパラダイスだ
ki ga tsukeba itsu datte
Before you know it,
気がつけば何時だって
ki ga tsukeba itsu datte
Before you know it,
uchouten jinsei da
you live a life of pure ecstasy
有頂天人生だ
uchouten jinsei da
you live a life of pure ecstasy
Episode Two
Mom and Raijin, God of Thunder
Looks like we ended up here again.
また来てしまったよ
Come on in, Prince.
いらっしゃい王子　今日のお供はお嬢さんか
I see you're with a fine young lady today.
If I'd known you were coming,
I would've had those folk wait for you.
来るんだって分かってれば
連中を待たしとくんだったな
Who do you mean?
誰のことだい？
Some men from a TV station.
ああ テレビ局の連中だよ
They wanted to interview the "Prince in Black"
.that the whole town's talking about.
街で噂の黒服の王子を取材したいってさ
Seems like I couldn't live
.a quiet life even if I wanted to.
僕に日陰の暮らしはできそうにもない
Wherever I go, towns buzz
.with gossip in my wake.
どこにいても噂になってしまう
Right. Then I'll give them
.the go-ahead next time I see them.
ああそう
じゃあ今度来たら取材OKって言っとくわ
Yashirou told me earlier that
you were out again yesterday—
出がけに矢四郎から聞いたのだが
昨日 君はまた
You can talk normally, Mother.
普通に話していいですよ 母上
No one's listening.
誰もいません
Did you go to meet with
Benten again yesterday?
昨日また弁天様と会ったのかい？
Yeah. Kinda.
ええ まあ
Must you act so recklessly?
またそんな危ないことをして
No need to worry.
大丈夫ですよ
That woman isn't right in the head.
You'll end up in her stew pot if you aren't careful.
あの人は無茶だから 油断してると鍋にされてしまうよ
Though tanuki have always been
...cursed with that fate...
昔から狸は鍋にされるものだけれども
The point is, humans are even more cunning,
sly, and wicked than tengu or foxes.
とにかく人間というのは
天狗や狐よりも陰険で質が悪いのだから
It was a personal request
.from Master Akadama.
赤玉先生に頼まれたんだから
I had no choice.
しょうがないや
はあ
His infatuations are always
.so unbefitting of his age.
先生も年甲斐のないことにうつつを抜かすのだから
People like him are the most
.troublesome to deal with.
ああいう人が一番困るわね
Ah, it's the Prince!
あ 王子いる
Well, if it isn't Andy!
よう アンディーじゃないか
The name's Ando.
アンドウですよ
Ready for our rematch?
どうすか リベンジ
I was born ready, Andy!
望むところさアンディー
I'm going to visit Yajirou.
矢二郎兄さんの所に行ってきます
Are you?
あらそうなの？
Check if he's still alive for me, will you?
じゃ ちゃんと生きてるか見てきてちょうだい
You could just go see
.him yourself, you know.
母上も会いに行けばいいのに
Have you ever been to his place?
一度も行ったことがないんでしょう？
I don't think he'd like that.
あの子は私が行くのを嫌がるから
He's living there because
.that's what he believes in,
あそこでああしているのはあの子の信念だけれど
but he'd be embarrassed
.if I saw him like that.
私にはそのことを恥じているのよ
The weather isn't good today,
so don't stay out too long, Mother.
今日は天気が悪いから 母上もほどほどに
Yasaburou, could you drop by the
Ebisugawa power plant on your way home?
矢三郎
帰りに夷川の発電所へ寄って
I need you to pick up Yashirou.
矢四郎を迎えに行ってあげなさい
Prince, which table should we use?
王子 台どっちでやります？
That one right there!
そちらへお邪魔しよう
I'm sorry!
ごめんなさい
あーあ
Shimogamo Yashirou,
how many times does that make?
下鴨矢四郎　お前 これで何度目？
You don't even have enough left
.for it to come out of your pay.
もう差し引くほどのお給金残ってないよ
You're in debt now. In the red!
借金だね 借金
But he bumped into me!
でもぶつかってきたのは
So now you're trying to pin
the blame on someone else?
人のせいにするのか
Big bro, I hope you'll show him
.the error of his ways.
兄さんビシーッと言ってやってよ
Meiwaku-senban!
迷惑千万
Huh?
へ？
It means "great nuisance."
It's an old idiom you can use
ありもしない事実で因縁をふっかけてきた相手を
to scold people who accuse others
.based on flimsy pretexts.
ひどく罵倒してやる時に使う四文字熟語だ
You're amazing, big bro.
うわあ さすが兄さん
That deserves a round of applause.
もう拍手喝采
You can work on cleaning
.that up until we get back.
次 戻ってきた時までに片付けとけよ
Yes, clean it all up.
片付けとけよ
This is why I can't stand
.those Shimogamo folk.
これだから下鴨一家の連中は
Indeed, neither can I.
ほんとほんと　これだから
Meiwaku-senban...
迷惑千万
Well, this is just another
.part of my training.
いや これも修行だ
The
Six
Paths
May
All
Rest
In
Peace
Big bro?
兄さん
Is that you, Yasaburou?
矢三郎かよ
I can't see you.
見えない
Oh, whatever.
まいっか
I'll eat my dinner here.
It's a beef bowl.
晩飯の牛丼ここで食うよ？
That sounds delicious.
牛丼はうまかろうな
It's a real tragedy you got so used to that form
.that you can't shape-shift anymore.
その姿が板に付き過ぎて
元の姿に戻れなくなったというのは
あまりに悲劇だよ
Have you been trying, at least?
ちょっとは練習したのかい？
I got pretty depressed the first night
.I realized I was stuck like this,
どうもダメらしいと分かった晩は
ちょっとしんみりしたけど
but I've resigned myself to it since then.
まあもう諦めはついたな
Besides, I never intended to go back
.to being a tanuki in the first place.
それに元々狸に戻る気は無かったんだぜ？
So I just got what I wanted, really.
願ったり叶ったりだよ
Do many people still come here?
まだ大勢来るの？
It's a lot quieter than it was last year.
まあ去年よりは落ち着いたけれども
Back when I was a tanuki, even the
.youngest pups made fun of me,
かつて狸であった頃は
子狸たちにすらバカ呼ばわりされていた俺が
but now so many people come to me
.that I'd actually like some time to myself.
今じゃ一人になる時間が欲しいくらい
人が集まってくる
In fact, there's no time to be lonely at all.
寂しがってる暇も無い
You wanna bury me alive
under your troubles?!
俺を悩み事で生き埋めにする気か
ん
On one hand, most people probably
.feel pretty dumb talking into a well,
ま 誰にしたってただの穴ぼこに向かって
喋りかけるのはバカバカしいし
but on the other hand, having someone listen to their troubles makes them feel a little better.
かと言って誰かが悩みを聞いてくれないと
張り合いもない
I'm an almost-forgotten almost-tanuki
.almost-outcast by my kin.
その点 俺は狸界から半ば退場して
忘れ去られた地狸だ
あむ
I can never change my form again.
蛙から元に戻ることは二度とない
And I'm always here at the
.bottom of the well, waiting.
いつ来ても井戸の底にいるのは分かってる
I guess the convenience of those three factors
.is what makes my well so popular.
このコンビニエントな感じがヒットの要因だろうね
Do you give advice and stuff too?
兄さんは何か助言したりするのかい？
Well, I don't really care
.about their problems.
他の連中のことなんぞ俺はどうでもいいからな
Sometimes it's better if the listener
.stays detached, anyway.
それに
時には親身にならない聞き手の方が
いいこともあるだろうさ
I'm just a small frog in a big well.
何せ井の中の蛙ですから
I know nothing of the great wide world.
大海を知らんのですから
So, you don't care about Mother
or the rest of us, either?
俺たちや母上のこともどうでもいいのかい？
Give me a little credit.
I'm not rotten to the core.
おいおい
俺もそこまで腐ってはいないぜ？
But you see, I'm a frog now.
でもなあ 何せ蛙だからな
By the way, Yaichirou stopped by the other day.
そういやこの間 矢一郎兄さんが来た
He did? What for?
げ 兄貴が？
何で？
Something must've been troubling him.
何か悩み事があったんだろう
He left without so much as a word, though.
黙ったまま帰ったけれども
Maybe he came to lecture you
but gave up and left?
説教しようとして諦めたんじゃないか？
Didn't seem that way to me.
そんな感じでもなかった
He has his share of troubles too, you know.
おい あいつにも悩み事は多いんだぜ
Yeah, I know.
分かってるよ
そんなことは
あああむ
I pity him sometimes.
俺はこの頃兄さんがつくづく可哀想になるんだ
He's trying so hard to be a worthy successor
.to our great father, Shimogamo Souichirou,
偉大なる父
下鴨総一郎の跡目を継いで
生真面目に踏ん張っているのに
but his brothers are a frog,
an idiot, and a kid.
弟たちが蛙と阿呆と坊やだからな
We're utterly useless.
屁の役にも立たん
I can't argue with that, nor do I want to.
反論できない
するつもりもない
You know, Yasaburou...
なあ矢三郎
ん？
You were always our father's favorite.
父上はお前を一番買っていたんだぜ
He even told Master Akadama
.to pay special attention to you.
赤玉先生にも あいつには特別に
気をかけてくれと言ったそうだ
"He's the most like me," he said.
あいつが一番俺に似た子だってな
That's the first I've heard of it.
そんなこと 初めて聞いた
Do you remember his last words to you?
お前
父上から最後に聞いた言葉を覚えているか
No.
いや
I can't remember his last words,
no matter how much I try.
俺は父上の最後の言葉がどうしても思い出せない
It still bothers me, even now.
それが今でも悔しくてな
ん？　おい
Hey, where's Mother?
母上はどこだ
At the billiards saloon as always.
例によってビリヤード場
Why do you ask?
何故？
There's a big one coming.
これからご立派なのが来るぜ
I can feel it in my butt.
何だか尻がむずむずするよ
あ
Raijin, God of Thunder,
has made his appearance.
雷神様のご到着だ
Tokusei Bridge
I gotta pick up Yashirou.
矢四郎を拾っていかなきゃ
Tokusei Bridge
あ
Yashirou...
矢四郎
あ　く
Back in
the Game
ああ
あ
ふっ
Shimogamo Yasaburou...
下鴨矢三郎
joins the fray!
見参
Bro!
兄ちゃん
Back in
the Game
Well, well. Yasaburou's here too.
おやおや 矢三郎が来たよ
Back in
the Game
どおん
Back in
the Game
Higuchi
Ichiyou
Back in
the Game
フフフ
ハハハ
フフ フフフ アハハハ
ハハハハハ
Fake Denki Bran factory
Ebisugawa power plant
Yasaburou, your brother abandoned his work
.and ran away from our factory.
矢三郎 その弟は仕事を放ったらかして
うちの工場を逃げ出したのだよ
That's not true!
そうじゃないよ
It's just that our mother
can't stand thunder, so I had to—
母上は雷が苦手だから
We were kind enough to let you work for us
.because you said you wanted training.
こっちは修行したいって言うから
働かせてやってるんだぞ
That's been quite a bit of trouble in itself.
それだけでも迷惑なのに
We can't just let you leave
.your work half-finished.
途中で仕事を投げられたらたまったものじゃないね
Indeed. It's just as you say, big bro.
全くそうだよ兄さん
We can't.
たまったものじゃない
When you can carry out the work
that's given to you prop—
自分に与えられた仕事を
文句を言わずにきちんとやり遂げてこそ
Drop dead!
くたばれ
...properly, only then
.will you be an adult.
いい 一人前なのさ
I really don't want to poke
my nose in your bus—
首を突っ込みたくはないけれど
Drop dead!
くたばれ
...business, but I'm worried about
.the future of the Shimogamo family.
下鴨一族の行く末が心配になってしまうよ
僕は
The Shimogamos are all so undisciplined.
下鴨家は半端な奴らばっかりさ 兄さん
The second-eldest brother is a frog,
次男は蛙だし 三男は阿呆だし
the third is an idiot, and the youngest
.brother is who you see before you.
末の弟もやーっぱりこの程度だしね
We Ebisugawas should try to
.set a good example for them.
我ら夷川一族がしっかりしなくちゃ
If we don't, the future of all
.tanuki-kind could be in danger.
狸界の未来も暗いね
Higuchi
Ichiyou
As long as you're here, big bro,
we've got nothing to worry about.
兄さんがいるから大丈夫だよ
You are like a beacon of hope to us.
いわゆる一つの希望の星という奴さ
Ginkaku...
銀閣 樋口一葉は人の名前で
"Higuchi Ichiyou" is a person's name,
not an idiom.
四文字熟語じゃないぞ
Higuchi
Ichiyou
You can't fool me.
そんなことじゃ騙されないね
You just don't know this idiom!
お前は四文字熟語博士か
Big bro, is he right?
兄さんそうなのかい？
No, don't listen to him.
ああ ああ信じてはいけない
Higuchi-ichiyou means "a fallen leaf,
caught in the rain gutter."
樋口一葉というのは
雨樋の端に濡れた枯れ葉が
一枚引っかかっているということさ
秋の淋しさを表した四文字熟語だ
It's an old idiom that expresses
.the solemnity of autumn.
I read it once in a book.
僕は本で読んだことがある
さすがだよ兄さん 僕も大方は分かっていたんだ
You're so knowledgeable, big bro!
.I knew it was something like that.
Now, let us take care of your brother.
さ そのーちびっこい弟をこちらへ渡せよ
We'll teach him an important lesson.
僕たちがお灸を据えてやる
ああ
Our father has given us total authority.
父上から全権を委任されているのだからね
It's our job to teach him about
.the hardships of labor.
仕事の厳しさを教えてやるのが僕らの仕事だ
And we take our job very seriously.
そして僕たちは仕事を途中で放り出したりはしない
So let us...
だからその弟を
Not a chance.
ごめんこうむる
You're as headstrong as always.
お前は相変わらず自分勝手だね
People like you who thumb their noses at tanuki
.societal norms are a constant thorn in my side.
お前みたいに狸界の掟を
ないがしろにする奴がいるのは
嘆かわしいことだと常々僕は思っている
And I've long thought that people like you
.are the least qualified to preach to me.
お前たちにだけは言われたくないと
俺も常々思っているよ
Believe me, we're qualified.
After all, we're great.
僕らはいいんだ 何故なら偉いんだもの
Bro, Mother's in trouble.
兄ちゃん 母上が困ってるよ
I know. We should retreat for now,
分かってる
ここは一旦 退却し その後 練りに練った卑劣な策で
and come back with a perfectly crafted revenge plan
.that'll really make them regret this.
ぐうの音も出んほど
Kinkaku! Ginkaku!
金閣 銀閣よ
は
あ
あー
ああ
んんん
Yaichirou!
矢一郎兄さん
があう
はあん
がう
きゃあ
He bit my butt!
お尻が割れた
があ うう
I'm flying! Someone catch me!
飛んでるよ 誰か受け止めて
あああああ
お おのれ鴨虎　いや下鴨矢一郎
Damn you, tanuki tiger.
I mean, Shimogamo Yaichirou.
うわ はあ
あ ああ
ううううううんん
んん
うう わはああ
がるるる
んん
うう
う く
わお
あ
Not there!
そこはダーメ　あは
そこは噛んではいろいろとヤバイってば
Please don't bite me there!
あっはあ
あ
What are you waiting for?! Get on!
何をぐずぐずしているんだ
早く乗れ
Why did you just let those Ebisugawas
walk all over you like that?!
何故お前たちは夷川の連中にあれだけ侮辱されて
何もやり返さないのだ？
Didn't you think for one moment
about defending the honor of our family?!
身を挺して一族の誇りを守ろうとする
気概は無いのか
Remind me, what exactly is the "honor of our family"?
一族の誇りとはなんぞや？
I can't quite recall.
俺には分からんね
I guess I shouldn't have expected someone
.who only cares about having fun to understand.
自分ばかりが面白ければそれで
いいという奴にはそりゃ分からんだろう
You bring shame to our parents' names!
全くお前は親不孝者だ
Our father must be spinning in his grave!
父上は冥土で悲しんでいるに決まってる
He wasn't the kind of tanuki who
.cared about family honor and stuff.
父上はそんなことを気にするような狸ではない
But I told them to drop dead!
でも兄さん 僕くたばれって言って…
Where's the Prince in Black?
黒服の王子は？
As soon as the thunder began,
the prince freaked out and split.
雷が鳴った途端 何かバタバタしてたけど
I dunno where to, because of all that commotion with the tanuki.
狸騒動でもうよく分かんなくなってさ
What commotion?
狸騒動？
そこのカフェに狸が出たって
A tanuki showed up over there.
What happened to it?
その狸はどうなった？
Not sure. Guess it disappeared at some point.
ああ いつの間にかどこかに行ったよ
はははは う
Thank you very much.
ありがとう
ああはああ 母上 玉突きなんぞしてるからだ
Mother! This is what happens
when you poke balls with sticks!
We should send out word immediately
こうなったら早急に伝令を走らせて
and get all the tanuki in the area
to form a search party!
洛中の全狸に呼び掛け
母上の一大捜索を断行しよう
Isn't that overreacting a little?
いくら何でも大げさだよ兄貴
Then what should we do?
You want her to get hit by a car again?!
だがまた車に跳ね飛ばされたらどうする
Why would she run all
the way to Gojo or Shijo?
だからって母上がわざわざ五条や
四条くんだりまで逃げると思うか？
We should split up and look
.here, around the bridge.
とにかく橋の周りを手分けして探そう
Right! Maybe that'd be best.
ああ そうだ さ それが先決だ
I'll take command!
あ では俺が指揮を執ろう
Yaichirou, you go and search
near Doshisha University!
まず矢一郎は同志社大学の方向を
Oh wait, I'm Yaichirou.
あ いや 矢一郎は俺か
Okay! I'll search near
Doshisha University!
俺が同志社の方を探す
Yasaburou, search the north
bank of the Kamo River!
ああ 矢三郎は鴨川の北を 矢四郎は橋の向こうだ
Yashirou, you can check the
.other side of the bridge.
As for the south...
Yasaburou, you go that way!
鴨川の南は矢三郎 お前が探せ
I can't go north and south
.at the same time.
北と南 同時には行けないよ
Then, Yajirou!
あ じゃあ 矢二郎だ
He's still in the well.
矢二郎兄さんは井戸の中だ
Also, he's a frog.
その上 蛙だ
How damn useless can a tanuki get?!
どこまで役に立たなければ気が済むんだあいつは
Why do I have to put up with such
utterly useless brothers? Is this my fate?!
何の因果だ 何故俺の弟たちは
こんなに役に立たない奴ばかりなんだ
Calm down, big bro.
落ち着いてくれ兄貴
I'm most worried about you at this point.
あんたが一番危なっかしい
く くう
For now, let's just split up and look for her.
とにかく手分けして捜そう
あ く
Found her yet?
いたか
No.
いや
どこ行っちゃったんだろう
Where could she have gone?
ん？
あ
ん
Mother!
母上
Thank goodness.
良かった
くしゅん
Oh no!
いかん
Were you under that bridge all this time?
ずっと橋の下にいたの？
The Ebisugawa girl was with me.
夷川の娘が一緒にいてくれたわ
She saved me when I was
.about to fall into the river.
もう少しで川に落ちる所をあの子が拾ってくれて
Mother! Come on!
母上 こちらへ
Is that you, Kaisei?
海星か？
How long are you gonna stand there?
いつまでそこにいるんだよ
Hurry up and get out of here.
早く帰れよ
I just wanted to say thanks.
いや 礼を言わんと
Don't waste your time.
そんなことはいいよ
Your mother's gonna catch a cold, stupid.
お母さんを風邪引かす気かよ
この阿呆が
Thank you.
ありがとう
Say hi to your stupid brothers,
Kinkaku and Ginkaku, for me,
金閣と銀閣のクソ兄貴共に
よろしく伝えてくれたまえ
though they might not
.be home for a while.
しばらく帰ってこられないかもしれないが
Take care on the way home.
気を付けて帰れ
What took you so long?
何をしていた？
I had to say thanks.
礼を言ってきた
The world would be a better place
.without those damn Ebisugawas,
夷川の奴らは残らずクタバレばいいけれど
but that girl is different.
あの子だけは別だね
I'm so happy I have you.
お前たちがいて良かったよ
Your father may have left us,
but you three are still here for me.
総さんがいなくても
私にはお前たちがいるのだから
Our father was a great tanuki who was
.known far and wide across the city.
我が父は洛中に名高い立派な狸であった
Respected by many,
he united local tanuki society.
大勢の狸たちから敬われ
その威光で狸界を束ねてきたが
Sadly, a few years ago,
he didn't come back home.
無念なことに数年前に帰らぬ狸となった
He was eaten.
喰われたのだ
鍋の具として
Made into stew.
When we got word of our father's death,
父が死んだと分かった時
the three of us were in such shock that it was
.half a day before we could even start to cry.
我々兄弟は半日ばかりも唖然として
それからようやく泣き出した
ああ うう
Any one of us tanuki could wind up in a stew.
狸として生きる限り 鍋にされることもある
It's just a normal part of life.
何の珍しいことがありますか
You must all become wonderful tanuki
that wouldn't bat an eyelid at becoming stew!
金曜倶楽部の鍋なんぞ鼻で笑ってあしらえる
器の大きな狸におなりなさい
けれども それを実地に試すことはないのよ
But don't ever try that yourselves.
Please, promise me none of you will ever end up in a stew!
お願いだから あなたたちだけは鍋にならないで
う ああ
ううああ ああ ああ
We grew up into great tanuki,
just like you asked, Mother,
母上の言ったように
器の大きい子供たちに育ったけれど
but the three of us are utterly useless.
うち三匹は役立たずだ
And the other one is a frog.
さらに言えば一匹は蛙だ
ふん
I don't mind what you become,
be it a frog or anything else.
蛙でも何でも構わないよ
It's enough for me to
.have you here in this world.
あなたたちがこの世にいるだけで私は十分
Not to mention, you really
.have become great tanuki.
それにあなたたちは皆 立派な狸だものね
Your mother knows.
お母さんには分かっているよ
Our mother doesn't think for one moment that
.her sons are famous losers among tanuki society.
我が母は自分の子供たちが
狸界に名高いダメ狸たちであるとは
毛ほども信じていない
She still solidly believes that we are all
.perfectly fit to succeed our great father.
我が子は一人残らず
今は亡き父の跡目を継ぐにふさわしい狸だと
信じて疑わない
Our father was great indeed,
我らの父は偉大であったが
but, you know, so is our mother.
母もまた偉大であった
繋いだ手を振りほどけば
You shake off my hand
tsunaida te wo furihodokeba
いたずらに　君微笑む
and idly smile at me
itazura ni kimi hohoemu
春は嵐　ざわざわする
Spring is ripe with the roll of thunder,
haru wa arashi zawazawa suru
and some cherry blossoms have already left the branches
mou hanabira chirisubonda
もう花びら散りすぼんだ
口癖はケセラセラ
Your favorite phrase is "Que será, será"
kuchiguse wa que sera sera
また呟く声がする
I can hear you whisper it again
mata tsubuyaku koe ga suru
彼女はいつもさよなら言わずに
She always vanishes
kanojo wa itsumo
sayonara
without saying "Goodbye,"
iwazu ni
風と消える
just like the wind
kaze to kieru
I don't know what the future will be like,
mirai no koto wa wakaranai keredo
未来のことはわからないけれど
今ここにある奇蹟は僕のものと
but I'll have faith
ima koko ni aru
that little miracles
kiseki wa
are awaiting me
boku no mono to shinjiteru
信じてる
約束なんてしたくないけれど
I don't want to be tied down by promises,
yakusoku nante shitakunai keredo
but let's hold up our hands
sono te wo kazashite
その手をかざして確かなもの
and find something,
tashika na mono
手に入れよう
something permanent
te ni ireyou
それは僕らを輝かす
that will
sore wa
show just who we are
bokura wo kagayakasu
何 弁天が？
Benten did what?!
How shameless! How inappropriate!
何と破廉恥なけしからん
見てはならぬ わし以外は見てはならぬぞ
Don't look!
Next Time:
Yakushibou's Inner Parlor
None other than me may look!